<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-reddy-dprive-bootstrap-dns-server-04"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="DoT/DoH server discovery">A Bootstrapping Procedure to
    Discover and Authenticate DNS-over-(D)TLS and DNS-over-HTTPS
    Servers</title>

    <author fullname="Tirumaleswar Reddy" initials="T." surname="Reddy">
      <organization abbrev="McAfee">McAfee, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Embassy Golf Link Business Park</street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>Karnataka</region>

          <code>560071</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>kondtir@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dan Wing" initials="D." surname="Wing">
      <organization abbrev="Citrix">Citrix Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>dwing-ietf@fuggles.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Michael C. Richardson" initials="M."
            surname="Richardson">
      <organization>Sandelman Software Works</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mcr+ietf@sandelman.ca</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mohamed Boucadair" initials="M." surname="Boucadair">
      <organization>Orange</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Rennes</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>35000</code>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mohamed.boucadair@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="7" month="May" year="2019" />

    <workgroup>DPRIVE WG</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies mechanisms to automatically bootstrap
      endpoints (e.g., hosts, Customer Equipment) to discover and authenticate
      DNS-over-(D)TLS and DNS-over-HTTPS servers provided by a local
      network.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>Traditionally a caching DNS server has been provided by local
      networks. This provides benefits such as low latency to reach that DNS
      server (owing to its network proximity to the endpoint). However, if an
      endpoint is configured to use Internet-hosted or public DNS-over-(D)TLS
      <xref target="RFC7858"></xref> <xref target="RFC8094"></xref> or
      DNS-over-HTTPS <xref target="RFC8484"></xref> servers, any available
      local DNS server cannot serve DNS requests from local endpoints. If
      public DNS servers are used instead of using local DNS servers, some
      operational problems can occur such as those listed below:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>"Split DNS" <xref target="RFC2775"></xref> to use the special
          internal-only domain names (e.g., "internal.example.com") in
          enterprise networks will not work, and ".local" and "home.arpa"
          names cannot be locally resolved in home networks.</t>

          <t>Content Delivery Networks (CDNs) that map traffic based on DNS
          may lose the ability to direct end-user traffic to a nearby
          service-specific cluster in cases where a DNS service is being used
          that is not affiliated with the local network and which does not
          send "EDNS Client Subnet" (ECS) information <xref
          target="RFC7871"></xref> to the CDN's DNS authorities <xref
          target="CDN"></xref>.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>If public DNS servers are used instead of using local DNS servers,
      the following discusses the impact on network-based security:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Various network security services are provided by Enterprise
          networks to protect endpoints (e.g,. Hosts, IoT devices). <xref
          target="I-D.camwinget-tls-use-cases"></xref> discusses some of the
          network-based security service use cases. These network security
          services act on DNS requests originating from endpoints.</t>

          <t>However, if an endpoint is configured to use public
          DNS-over-(D)TLS or DNS-over-HTTPS servers, network security services
          cannot act efficiently on DNS requests from these endpoints.</t>

          <t>In order to act on DNS requests from endpoints, network security
          services can block DNS-over-(D)TLS traffic by dropping outgoing
          packets to destination port 853. Identifying DNS-over-HTTPS traffic
          is far more challenging than DNS-over-(D)TLS traffic. Network
          security services may try to identify the domains offering
          DNS-over-HTTPS servers, and DNS-over-HTTPS traffic can be blocked by
          dropping outgoing packets to these domains. If an endpoint has
          enabled strict privacy profile (Section 5 of <xref
          target="RFC8310"></xref>), and the network security service blocks
          the traffic to the public DNS server, the DNS service won't be
          available to the endpoint and ultimately the endpoint cannot access
          Internet-reachable services.</t>

          <t>If an endpoint has enabled opportunistic privacy profile (Section
          5 of <xref target="RFC8310"></xref>), and the network security
          service blocks traffic to the public DNS server, the endpoint will
          either fallback to an encrypted connection without authenticating
          the DNS server provided by the local network or fallback to clear
          text DNS, and cannot exchange encrypted DNS messages.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>If the network security service fails to block DNS-over-(D)TLS or
      DNS-over-HTTPS traffic, this can compromise the endpoint security; some
      of the potential security threats are listed below:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>The network security service cannot prevent an endpoint from
          accessing malicious domains.</t>

          <t>If the endpoint is an IoT device which is configured to use
          public DNS-over-(D)TLS or DNS-over-HTTPS servers, and if a policy
          enforcement point in the local network is programmed using, for
          example, a Manufacturer Usage Description (MUD) file <xref
          target="RFC8520"></xref> by a MUD manager to only allow intented
          communications to and from the IoT device, the policy enforcement
          point cannot enforce the network Access Control List (ACL) rules
          based on domain names (Section 8 of <xref
          target="RFC8520"></xref>).</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>If the network security service successfully blocks DNS-over-(D)TLS
      and DNS-over-HTTPS traffic, this can still compromise the endpoint
      security and privacy; some of the potential security threats are listed
      below:<list style="symbols">
          <t>Pervasive monitoring of DNS traffic.</t>

          <t>An internal attacker can modify the DNS responses to re-direct
          the client to malicious servers.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>To overcome the above threats, this document specifies a mechanism to
      automatically bootstrap endpoints to discover and authenticate the
      DNS-over-(D)TLS and DNS-over-HTTPS servers provided by their local
      network. The overall procedure can be structured into the following
      steps:<list style="symbols">
          <t><xref target="bootstrap-endpoint">Bootstrapping</xref> is
          necessary only when connecting to a new network or when the
          network's DNS certificate has changed. Bootstrapping authenticates
          the Enrollment over Secure Transport (EST) <xref
          target="RFC7030"></xref> server to the endpoint. After
          authenticating the EST server, DNS server certificate used by the
          local network is downloaded to the endpoint. This DNS server
          certificate enables subsequent authenticated encrypted communication
          with the local DNS server (e.g., DNS-over-HTTPS) during in the
          connection phase.</t>

          <t><xref target="discovery">Discovery</xref> is performed by a
          previously bootstrapped endpoint whenever connecting to a network.
          During discovery, the endpoint is instructed which privacy-enabling
          DNS protocol(s), port number(s), and IP addresses are supported on a
          local network. This effectively takes the place of DNS server IP
          address traditionally provided by IPv4 or IPv6 DHCP or by <xref
          target="RFC8106">IPv6 Router Advertisement</xref>.</t>

          <t><xref target="auth">Connection handshake and service
          invocation</xref>: The DNS client initiates a (D)TLS handshake with
          the DNS server learned in the discovery phase, and validates the DNS
          server's identity using the credentials obtained in the
          bootstrapping phase.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Note: The strict and opportunistic privacy profiles as defined in
      <xref target="RFC8310"></xref> only applies to DNS-over-(D)TLS
      protocols, there has been no such distinction made for DNS-over-HTTPS
      protocol.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="scope" title="Scope">
      <t>The problems discussed in <xref target="intro"></xref> will be
      encountered in Enterprise networks. Typically Enterprise networks do not
      assume that all devices in their network are managed by the IT team or
      Mobile Device Management (MDM) devices, especially in the quite common
      BYOD ("Bring Your Own Device") scenario. The mechanisms specified in
      this document can be used by BYOD devices to discover and authenticate
      DNS-over-(D)TLS and DNS-over-HTTPS servers provided by the Enterprise
      network. This mechanism can also be used by IoT devices (managed by IT
      team) after onboarding to discover and authenticate DNS-over-(D)TLS and
      DNS-over-HTTPS servers provided by the Enterprise network.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="notation" title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
      <xref target="RFC2119"></xref><xref target="RFC8174"></xref> when, and
      only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>

      <t>(D)TLS is used for statements that apply to both Transport Layer
      Security <xref target="RFC8446"></xref> and Datagram Transport Layer
      Security <xref target="RFC6347"></xref>. Specific terms are used for any
      statement that applies to either protocol alone.</t>

      <t>This document uses the terms defined in <xref
      target="RFC8499"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="bootstrap-endpoint"
             title="Bootstrapping Endpoint Devices">
      <t>The following steps detail the mechanism to automatically bootstrap
      an endpoint with the local network's DNS server certificate: <list
          style="numbers">
          <t>The endpoint authenticates to the local network and discovers the
          Enrollment over Secure Transport (EST) <xref
          target="RFC7030"></xref> server using the procedure discussed in
          <xref target="EST_Discovery"></xref>.</t>

          <t>The endpoint establishes provisional TLS connection with that EST
          server, i.e., the endpoint provisionally accepts the unverified TLS
          server certificate. However, the endpoint MUST authenticate the EST
          server before it accepts the DNS server certificate. The endpoint
          either uses password-based authenticated key exchange (PAKE) with
          TLS 1.3 <xref target="I-D.barnes-tls-pake"></xref> as an
          authentication method or uses the mutual authentication protocol for
          HTTP <xref target="RFC8120"> </xref> to authenticate the discovered
          EST server. <vspace blankLines="1" />As a reminder, PAKE is an
          authentication method that allows the use of usernames and passwords
          over unencrypted channels without revealing the passwords to an
          eavesdropper. Similarly, the mutual authentication for HTTP is based
          on PAKE and provides mutual authentication between an HTTP client
          and an HTTP server using username and password as credentials. The
          cryptographic algorithms to use with the mutual authentication
          protocol for HTTP are defined in <xref target="RFC8121"></xref>.</t>

          <t>The endpoint needs to use PAKE scheme to perform authentication
          the first time it connects to an EST server. If the EST server
          authentication is successful, the server's identity can be used to
          authenticate subsequent TLS connections to that EST server. The
          endpoint configures the reference identifier for the EST server
          using the DNS-ID identifier type in the EST server certificate. On
          subsequent connections to the EST server, the endpoint MUST validate
          the EST server certificate using the Implict Trust Anchor database
          (i.e, the EST server certificate must pass PKIX certification path
          validation) and match the reference identifier against the EST
          server's identity according to the rules specified in Section 6.4 of
          <xref target="RFC6125"></xref>.</t>

          <t>The endpoint learns the End-Entity certificates <xref
          target="RFC8295"></xref> from the EST server. The certificate
          provisioned to the DNS server in the local network will be treated
          as a End-Entity certificate. As a reminder, the End-Entity
          certificates must be validated by the endpoint using an authorized
          trust anchor (Section 3.2 of <xref target="RFC8295"></xref>). The
          endpoint needs to identify the certificate provisioned to the DNS
          server. The SRV-ID identifier type <xref target="RFC6125"></xref>
          within subjectAltName entry MUST be used to identify the DNS server
          certificate. <vspace blankLines="1" />For example, DNS server
          certificate will include SRV-ID "_domain-s.example.net" along with
          DNS-ID "example.net". The SRV service label "domain-s" is defined in
          Section 6 of <xref target="RFC7858"></xref>. As a reminder, the
          protocol component is not included in the SRV-ID <xref
          target="RFC4985"></xref>.</t>

          <t>The endpoint configures the authentication domain name (ADN)
          (defined in <xref target="RFC8310"></xref>) for the DNS server from
          the DNS-ID identifier type within subjectAltName entry in the DNS
          server certificate. The DNS server certificate is associated with
          the ADN to be matched with the certificate given by the DNS server
          in (D)TLS. To some extent, this approach is similar to certificate
          usage PKIX-EE(1) defined in <xref target="RFC7671"></xref>.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t><xref target="fig1"></xref> illustrates a sequence diagram for
      bootstrapping an endpoint with the local network's DNS server
      certificate.</t>

      <t><figure anchor="fig1" title="Bootstrapping Endpoint Devices">
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[                                                                                                                                                                                                     
+----------+                                     +--------+  +--------+                               
| Endpoint |                                     |  EST   |  |  DNS   |   
|          |                                     | Server |  | Server |                     
+----------+                                     +--------+  +--------+                               
        | DNS-SD query to discover the EST server      |          |                                         
        |-------------------------------------------------------->|                                         
        |                                              |          |
        | optional: mDNS query to                      |          |
        |  discover the EST server                     |          |
        |--------------------------------------------->|          | 
        |                                              |          |                                         
        | Establish provisional TLS connection         |          |                                         
        |<-------------------------------------------->|          |                                         
        |                                              |          |                                         
        | PAKE scheme to authenticate the EST server   |          | 
        |<-------------------------------------------->|          |                                         
        |                                              |          |                                         
[Generate reference identifier for the EST server      |          |                                         
 to compare with the EST server certificate            |          |
 in subsequent TLS connections]                        |          |                           
        |                                              |          |                                         
        |      Get EE certificates                     |          |                                         
        |--------------------------------------------->|          |                                         
        |                                              |          |                                         
[Identify the DNS server certificate in EE             |          | 
 certificates to match with the certificate            |          |  
 by the DNS server in (D)TLS handshake]                |          |                                          
                                                       |          |
[Configure ADN and associate DNS server certificate]   |          | 
        |                                              |          |                                         
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="bootstrap-iot" title="Bootstrapping IoT Devices">
      <t>The following steps explain the mechanism to automatically bootstrap
      IoT devices with local network's CA certificates and DNS server
      certificate: <list style="symbols">
          <t>Bootstrapping Remote Secure Key Infrastructures (BRSKI) discussed
          in <xref target="I-D.ietf-anima-bootstrapping-keyinfra"></xref>
          provides a solution for secure automated bootstrap of devices. BRSKI
          specifies means to provision credentials on devices to be used to
          operationally access networks. In addition, BRSKI provides an
          automated mechanism for the bootstrap distribution of CA
          certificates from the EST server. The IoT device can use BRSKI to
          automatically bootstrap the IoT device using the IoT manufacturer
          provisioned X.509 certificate, in combination with a registrar
          provided by the local network and IoT device manufacturer's
          authorizing service (MASA):<list style="numbers">
              <t>The IoT device authenticates to the local network using the
              IoT manufacturer provisioned X.509 certificate. The IoT device
              can request and get a voucher from the MASA service via the
              registrar. The voucher is signed by the MASA service and
              includes the local network's CA public key.</t>

              <t>The IoT device validates the signed voucher using the
              manufacturer installed trust anchor associated with the MASA,
              stores the CA's public key and validates the provisional TLS
              connection to the registrar.</t>

              <t>The IoT device requests the full EST distribution of current
              CA certificates (Section 5.9.1 in <xref
              target="I-D.ietf-anima-bootstrapping-keyinfra"></xref>) from the
              registrar operating as a BRSKI-EST server. The IoT devices
              stores the CA certificates as Explicit Trust Anchor database
              entries. The IoT device uses the Explicit Trust Anchor database
              to validate the DNS server certificate.</t>

              <t>The IoT device learns the End-Entity certificates from the
              BRSKI-EST server. The certificate provisioned to the DNS server
              in the local network will be treated as an End-Entity
              certificate. The IoT device needs to identify the certificate
              provisioned to the DNS server. The SRV-ID identifier type within
              subjectAltName entry MUST be used to identify the DNS server
              certificate.</t>

              <t>The endpoint configures the ADN for the DNS server from the
              DNS-ID identifier type within subjectAltName entry in the DNS
              server certificate. The DNS server certificate is associated
              with the ADN to be matched with the certificate given by the DNS
              server in (D)TLS.</t>
            </list></t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="discovery"
             title="DNS-over-(D)TLS and DNS-over-HTTPS Server Discovery Procedure">
      <t>This specification defines "DPRIVE" as the application service tag
      (<xref target="serviceT"></xref>) and "dns.tls" (<xref
      target="dnstls"></xref>), "dns.dtls" (<xref target="dnsdtls"></xref>),
      and "dns.https" (<xref target="dnshttps"></xref>) as application
      protocol tags. A DNS client discovers the DNS server in the local
      network supporting DNS-over-TLS, DNS-over-DTLS and DNS-over-HTTPS
      protocols by using the following discovery mechanism:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>The DNS client makes an S-NAPTR <xref target="RFC3958"></xref>
          lookup with the authentication domain name and the 'DPRIVE'
          application service tag to learn the protocols DNS-over-TLS,
          DNS-over-DTLS, and DNS-over-HTTPS supported by the DNS server and
          the DNS privacy protocol preferred by the DNS server administrators.
          The S-NAPTR lookup is performed using an recursive DNS resolver
          discovered from an untrusted source (such as DHCP).</t>

          <t>In the example depicted in <xref
          target="fig-naptr-lookup"></xref>, for authentication domain name
          'example.net', the resolution algorithm will result in the
          privacy-enabling protocols supported by the DNS server and usable
          DNS server IP addresses and port numbers.<figure
              anchor="fig-naptr-lookup">
              <artwork><![CDATA[   example.net.
   IN NAPTR 100 10 "" DPRIVE:dns.tls  "" dns1.example.net.
   IN NAPTR 200 10 "" DPRIVE:dns.dtls "" dns2.example.net.

   dns1.example.net.
   IN NAPTR 100 10 S DPRIVE:dns.tls "" _domain-s._tcp.example.net.

   dns2.example.net.
   IN NAPTR 100 10 S DPRIVE:dns.dtls "" _domain-s._udp.example.net.

   _domain-s._tcp.example.net.
   IN SRV   0 0 853 a.example.net.

   _domain-s._udp.example.net.
   IN SRV   0 0 853 a.example.net.

   a.example.net.
   IN A        192.0.2.1
   IN AAAA     2001:db8:8:4::2
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t>If DNS-over-HTTPS protocol is supported by the DNS server, the
          DNS client finds the URI template of the DNS-over-HTTPS server using
          one of the mechanisms discussed in <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-doh-resolver-associated-doh"> </xref> to use the
          https URI scheme (Section 3 of <xref target="RFC8484"></xref>).</t>

          <t>If no DNS-specific S-NAPTR records can be retrieved, the
          discovery procedure fails for this authentication domain name.
          However, before retrying a lookup that has failed, a DNS client MUST
          wait a time period that is appropriate for the encountered error
          (e.g., NXDOMAIN, timeout, etc.).</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="auth" title="Connection Handshake and Service Invocation">
      <t>The DNS client initiates (D)TLS handshake with the DNS server, the
      DNS server presents its certificate in ServerHello message, and the DNS
      client MUST match the DNS server certificate downloaded in Step 4 in
      <xref target="bootstrap-endpoint"></xref> or <xref
      target="bootstrap-iot"></xref> with the certificate provided by the DNS
      server in (D)TLS handshake. If the match is successful, the DNS client
      MUST validate the server certificate using the Implicit Trust Anchor
      database (i.e., the DNS server certificate must pass PKIX certification
      path validation).</t>

      <t>If the match is successful and server certificate is successfully
      validated, the client continues with the connection as normal.
      Otherwise, the client MUST treat the server certificate validation
      failure as a non-recoverable error. If the DNS client cannot reach or
      establish an authenticated and encrypted connection with the
      privacy-enabling DNS server provided by the local network, the DNS
      client can fallback to the privacy-enabling public DNS server.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="EST_Discovery" title="EST Service Discovery Procedure">
      <t>DNS-based Service Discovery (DNS-SD) <xref target="RFC6763"></xref>
      and Multicast DNS (mDNS) <xref target="RFC6762"></xref> provide generic
      solutions for discovering services available in a local network.
      DNS-SD/mDNS define a set of naming rules for certain DNS record types
      that they use for advertising and discovering services.</t>

      <t>Section 4.1 of <xref target="RFC6763"></xref> specifies that a
      service instance name in DNS-SD has the following structure:</t>

      <t>&lt;Instance&gt; . &lt;Service&gt; . &lt;Domain&gt;</t>

      <t>The &lt;Domain&gt; portion specifies the DNS sub-domain where the
      service instance is registered. It may be "local.", indicating the mDNS
      local domain, or it may be a conventional domain name such as
      "example.com.". The &lt;Service&gt; portion of the EST service instance
      name MUST be "_est._tcp".</t>

      <section title="mDNS">
        <t>A EST client application can proactively discover an EST server
        being advertised in the site by multicasting a PTR query to the
        following:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>"_est._tcp.local"</t>
          </list>A EST server can send out gratuitous multicast DNS answer
        packets whenever it starts up, wakes from sleep, or detects a change
        in EST server configuration. EST client application can receive these
        gratuitous packets and cache information contained in them.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="reattach" title="Network Reattachment">
      <t>On subsequent attachments to the network, the endpoint discovers the
      privacy-enabling DNS server using the authentication domain name
      (configured in Step 5 of <xref target="bootstrap-endpoint"></xref> or
      <xref target="bootstrap-iot"></xref>), initiates (D)TLS handshake with
      the DNS server and follows the mechanism discussed in <xref
      target="auth"></xref> to validate the DNS server certificate.</t>

      <t>If the DNS server certificate is invalid (e.g., revoked or expired)
      or the procedure to discover the privacy-enabling DNS server fails (e.g.
      the domain name of the privacy-enabling DNS server has changed because
      the Enterprise network has switched to a public privacy-enabling DNS
      server capable of blocking access to malicious domains), the endpoint
      discovers and initiates TLS handshake with the EST server, and uses the
      validation techniques described in <xref target="RFC6125"></xref> to
      compare the reference identifier (created in Step 2 of <xref
      target="bootstrap-endpoint"></xref> in this document) to the EST server
      certificate and verifies the entire certification path as per <xref
      target="RFC5280"></xref>. The endpoint then gets the DNS server
      certificate from the EST server. If the DNS-ID identifier type within
      subjectAltName entry in the DNS server certificate does not match the
      configured ADN, the ADN is replaced with the DNS-ID identifier type. The
      DNS server certificate associated with the ADN is replaced with the one
      provided by the EST server. If the ADN has changed, the endpoint
      discovers the privacy-enabling DNS server, initiates (D)TLS handshake
      with the DNS server and follows the mechanism discussed in <xref
      target="auth"></xref> to validate the DNS server certificate.</t>

      <t><xref target="fig2"></xref> illustrates a sequence diagram for
      re-configuring an endpoint with ADN and local network's DNS server
      certificate on subsequent attachments to the network.</t>

      <t><figure anchor="fig2"
          title="Bootstrapping Endpoint Devices on subsequent attachments to the network">
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[+----------+                                     +--------+  +--------+                               
| Endpoint |                                     |  EST   |  |  DNS   |   
|          |                                     | Server |  | Server |                     
+----------+                                     +--------+  +--------+                               
        | DNS-SD query to discover the EST server      |          |                                         
        |-------------------------------------------------------->|                                         
        |                                              |          |
        | optional: mDNS query to                      |          |
        | discover the EST server                      |          |
        |--------------------------------------------->|          | 
        |                                              |          |                                         
        | Establish TLS connection                     |          | 
        | and validate EST server certificate          |          |
        |<-------------------------------------------->|          |                                         
        |                                              |          |                                         
        |      Get EE certificates                     |          |                                         
        |<-------------------------------------------->|          |                                         
        |                                              |          |                                         
[Identify the DNS server certificate in EE             |          | 
 certificates to match with the certificate            |          |  
 by the DNS server in (D)TLS handshake]                |          |                                          
                                                       |          |
[Re-configure ADN and associate DNS server certificate]|          | 
        |                                              |          |

]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="privacy" title="Privacy Considerations">
      <t><xref target="RFC7626"></xref> discusses DNS privacy considerations
      in both "on the wire" (Section 2.4 of <xref target="RFC7626"></xref>)
      and "in the server" (Section 2.5 of <xref target="RFC7626"></xref>
      contexts. The endpoint may not know if the DNS-over-(D)TLS or
      DNS-over-HTTPS server in the local network has a privacy preserving data
      policy. A new privacy certificate extension is defined that identifies
      the privacy preserving data policy of the DNS server.</t>

      <section title="Privacy Extension Format">
        <t>Like all X.509 certificate extensions, the privacy certificate
        extension is defined using ASN.1 <xref target="ASN1-88"></xref>. The
        non-critical privacy extension is identified by id-pe-privacy.</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[   PKIX Object Identifier Registry

   id-pkix OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { iso(1) identified-organization(3)
              dod(6) internet(1) security(5) mechanisms(5) pkix(7) }

   PKIX Arcs
   id-mod  OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-pkix 0 }    -- modules
   id-pe   OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-pkix 1 }    -- private
   certificate extensions

   PKIX modules
   id-mod-privacy-extn         OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-mod TBD2 }
   id-pe-privacy OBJECT IDENTIFIER  ::=  { id-pe TBD1 }
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>A non-null privacy always includes a base privacy. The privacy
        extension includes the following information:<list style="symbols">
            <t>If the client IP address is Personally Identifiable Information
            (PII) data or non PII-data. If the client IP address is logged or
            not, and if client IP address is indeed logged, the period for
            which the client IP address is logged. Logging duration is
            represented in hours. A negative one (-1) of logging duration
            indicates indefinite duration. </t>

            <t>If the user identity is logged or not, and if user identity
            address is indeed logged, the period for which the user identity
            is logged. </t>

            <t>If the transaction data (e.g., DNS messages) is logged or not,
            and if transaction data is logged, the period for which the
            transaction data is stored. </t>

            <t>If the transaction data is logged to notify the user access to
            certain domains (e.g., malicious domains) is blocked, the period
            for which the transaction data is stored. If access to malicious
            domains is logged, the period for which the transaction data is
            stored. </t>

            <t>If the transaction data is logged for analytics (e.g. to detect
            malicious domains), the period for which the transaction data is
            stored. </t>

            <t>If the transaction data is shared with partners or not, and if
            the transaction data is shared with partners, the names of the
            partners. If anonymized data or client identifiable data is shared
            with partners.</t>

            <t>If the transaction data is shared or sold to third parties.</t>

            <t>If the DNS server will block DNS resolution of certain domains
            (e.g., malicious domains).</t>

            <t>A URL that points to the privacy preserving data policy, and a
            URL that points to the security assessment report of the DNS
            server by a third party auditor.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Privacy Extension Syntax">
        <t>The syntax for the privacy extension is as follows:</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[   Privacy ::=  CHOICE  {
     none                 NULL,             
                          -- No privacy policy provided
     pPolicy              PrivacyPolicy 
                          -- Privacy preserving data policy  }  
                          

   PrivacyPolicy ::=  SEQUENCE  {
     base              PrivacyInfo,
     pURL         [0]  PrivacyURL OPTIONAL,
     aURL         [1]  AuditURL OPTIONAL  }

  PrivacyInfo  ::=  SEQUENCE  {
    ipaddresspii      BOOLEAN,  
                      -- TRUE means client IP address is PII
    log          [0]  Logging, 
    sdata        [2]  ShareData,
    transferdata [3]  BOOLEAN,  
                      -- TRUE means share or sell data to third parties
    blockdomains [4]  BOOLEAN   
                      -- TRUE means domains will be blocked  }

   LoggingTypes  ::=  BIT STRING {
     none           (0), 
             -- No logging
     all            (1),
             -- Log all transaction data 
     clientip       (2), 
             -- Log client IP address
     useridentity   (3),
             -- Log user identity  
     notifyuser     (4),
             -- Log to notify user access 
             -- to certain domains is blocked
     knownmalware   (5),
             -- Log access to malicious domains
     analytics      (6)  
             -- Log transaction data for analytics 
             -- (e.g. to detect malicious domains) }
    
   LoggingDuration ::=  SEQUENCE {
        all            INTEGER OPTIONAL,
                       -- Number of Hours the logged 
                       -- transcation data is stored
        clientip       INTEGER OPTIONAL,
        useridentity   INTEGER OPTIONAL, 
        notifyuser     INTEGER OPTIONAL,
        knownmalware   INTEGER OPTIONAL,
        analytics      INTEGER OPTIONAL }

   Logging ::=  SEQUENCE  {
     loggingTypes         LoggingTypes DEFAULT {none},
     loggingDuration      LoggingDuration OPTIONAL   
                          -- Logged transaction data is cleared 
                          -- after logging duration.
                          -- negative one (-1) indicates indefinite 
                          -- duration  }

   ShareData ::=  SEQUENCE  {
     sharepartners        BOOLEAN, 
                          -- TRUE means data is shared with partners
     partners        [1]  SEQUENCE SIZE (1..MAX) OF UTF8String OPTIONAL, 
                          -- Names of the partners
     anonymizeddata  [0]  BOOLEAN OPTIONAL 
                          -- TRUE means anonymized data 
                          -- is shared with partners  }
 
   PrivacyURL  ::=  IA5String  -- MUST use https scheme
   AuditURL    ::=  IA5String  -- MUST use https scheme
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The bootstrapping procedure to obtain the certificate of the local
      networks DNS server uses a client identity and password to authenticate
      the EST server using PAKE schemes. Security considerations such as those
      discussed in <xref target="I-D.barnes-tls-pake"></xref> or <xref
      target="RFC8120"></xref> and <xref target="RFC8121"></xref> need to be
      taken into consideration.</t>

      <t>Users cannot be expected to enable or disable the bootstrapping or
      the discovery procedure as they switch networks. Thus, it is RECOMMENDED
      that users indicate to their system in some way that they desire
      bootstrapping to be performed when connecting to a specific network,
      similar to the way users disable VPN connection in specific network
      (e.g., Enterprise network) and enable VPN connection by default in other
      networks.</t>

      <t>If an endpoint has enabled strict privacy profile, and the network
      security service blocks the traffic to the privacy-enabling public DNS
      server, a hard failure occurs and the user is notified. The user has a
      choice to switch to another network or if the user trusts the network,
      the user can enable strict privacy profile with the DNS-over-(D)TLS or
      DNS-over-HTTPS server discovered in the network instead of downgrading
      to opportunistic privacy profile.</t>

      <t>The primary attacks against the methods described in <xref
      target="discovery"></xref> are the ones that would lead to impersonation
      of a DNS server and spoofing the DNS response to indicate that the DNS
      server does not support any privacy-enabling protocols. To protect
      against DNS-vectored attacks, secured DNS (DNSSEC) can be used to ensure
      the validity of the DNS records received. Impersonation of the DNS
      server is prevented by validating the certificate presented by the DNS
      server. If the EST server conveys the DNS server certificate, but the
      S-NAPTR lookup indicates that the DNS server does not support any
      privacy-enabling protocols, the client can detect the DNS response is
      spoofed.</t>

      <t>Security considerations in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-anima-bootstrapping-keyinfra"></xref> need to be taken
      into consideration for IoT devices.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>IANA is requested to allocate the SRV service name of "est".</t>

      <t>IANA is requested to add the following entry in the "SMI Security for
      PKIX Certificate Extension" (1.3.6.1.5.5.7.1) registry:</t>

      <t><figure>
          <preamble></preamble>

          <artwork><![CDATA[   Decimal  Description                     References
   -------  ------------------------------  ---------------------

     TBD1     id-pe-privacy                   this document 
]]></artwork>

          <postamble></postamble>
        </figure></t>

      <t>IANA is requested to add the following entry in the "SMI Security for
      PKIX Module Identifier" (1.3.6.1.5.5.7.0) registry:</t>

      <t><figure>
          <preamble></preamble>

          <artwork><![CDATA[   Decimal  Description                     References
   -------  ------------------------------  ---------------------

     TBD2     id-mod-privacy-extn           this document 
]]></artwork>

          <postamble></postamble>
        </figure></t>

      <section anchor="tag"
               title="Application Service &amp; Application Protocol Tags">
        <t>This document requests IANA to make the following allocations from
        the registry available at:
        https://www.iana.org/assignments/s-naptr-parameters/s-naptr-parameters.xhtml.</t>

        <section anchor="serviceT"
                 title="DNS Application Service Tag Registration">
          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>Application Protocol Tag: DPRIVE</t>

              <t>Intended Usage: See <xref target="discovery"></xref></t>

              <t>Security Considerations: See <xref
              target="Security"></xref></t>

              <t>Contact Information: &lt;one of the authors&gt;</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="dnstls"
                 title="dns.tls Application Protocol Tag Registration">
          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>Application Protocol Tag: dns.tls</t>

              <t>Intended Usage: See <xref target="discovery"></xref></t>

              <t>Security Considerations: See <xref
              target="Security"></xref></t>

              <t>Contact Information: &lt;one of the authors&gt;</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="dnsdtls"
                 title="dns.dtls Application Protocol Tag Registration">
          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>Application Protocol Tag: dns.dtls</t>

              <t>Intended Usage: See <xref target="discovery"></xref></t>

              <t>Security Considerations: See <xref
              target="Security"></xref></t>

              <t>Contact Information: &lt;one of the authors&gt;</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="dnshttps"
                 title="dns.https Application Protocol Tag Registration">
          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>Application Protocol Tag: dnshttps</t>

              <t>Intended Usage: See <xref target="discovery"></xref></t>

              <t>Security Considerations: See <xref
              target="Security"></xref></t>

              <t>Contact Information: &lt;one of the authors&gt;</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="acknowledgments" title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>Thanks to Joe Hildebrand, Harsha Joshi, Shashank Jain, Patrick
      McManus, Bob Harold, Livingood Jason, Eliot Lear and Sara Dickinson for
      the discussion and comments.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6125"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7030"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8295"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8484"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7858"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8094"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3958"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6763"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8499"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8446"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6347"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4985"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8121"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6762"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5280"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-doh-resolver-associated-doh'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8310"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8120"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.barnes-tls-pake'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-anima-bootstrapping-keyinfra'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2775"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8106"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7871"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7626"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8520'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7671'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.camwinget-tls-use-cases'?>

      <reference anchor="CDN"
                 target="https://conferences.sigcomm.org/sigcomm/2015/pdf/papers/p167.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>End-User Mapping: Next Generation Request Routing for Content
          Delivery</title>

          <author>
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2015" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="ASN1-88" target="">
        <front>
          <title>International Telephone and Telegraph Consultative Committee,
          "Specification of Abstract Syntax Notation One (ASN.1)", CCITT
          Recommendation X.208, 1988.</title>

          <author>
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date year="" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
